QUESTIONS = [
  {
    "question": "Limiting reactants are the reactants that are:",
    "options": {
      "A": "Not involved in the reaction",
      "B": "Used to start the reaction",
      "C": "In excess and remain after the reaction",
      "D": "Completely consumed in the reaction"
    },
    "answer": "D",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "The attraction between a partially positive hydrogen atom and a partially negative atom in another molecule is called a _________",
    "options": {
      "A": "Covalent bond",
      "B": "Metallic bond",
      "C": "Dipole-dipole interaction",
      "D": "Hydrogen bond"
    },
    "answer": "D",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "Solubility is the",
    "options": {
      "A": "Ability of a solid to change its shape",
      "B": "Tendency of a substance to undergo a chemical reaction",
      "C": "Measure of the concentration of a solution",
      "D": "Maximum amount of a solute that can dissolve in a solvent at a specific temperature"
    },
    "answer": "D",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "Stoichiometry is the study of the ________",
    "options": {
      "A": "Properties of elements",
      "B": "Equilibrium in chemical reactions",
      "C": "Quantitative relationships between reactants and products in a chemical reaction",
      "D": "Rates of chemical reactions"
    },
    "answer": "C",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "A balanced chemical equation shows _______",
    "options": {
      "A": "The energy change during the reaction",
      "B": "The rate of the reaction",
      "C": "The reactants and products, but not the quantities",
      "D": "The reactants and products, with their coefficients indicating quantities"
    },
    "answer": "D",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "The octet rule states that atoms tend to gain or lose electrons to achieve a valence shell with _______",
    "options": {
      "A": "1 electron",
      "B": "18 electrons",
      "C": "8 electrons",
      "D": "2 electrons"
    },
    "answer": "C",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which type of chemical bond involves the sharing of electrons between atoms?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Covalent bond",
      "B": "Hydrogen bond",
      "C": "Metallic bond",
      "D": "Ionic bond"
    },
    "answer": "A",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "Lewis structures use symbols to represent ________",
    "options": {
      "A": "Protons",
      "B": "Electrons",
      "C": "Neutrons",
      "D": "Isotopes"
    },
    "answer": "B",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "The common ion effect describes how the presence of a common ion in a solution",
    "options": {
      "A": "Reduces the solubility of the ionic compound that shares the ion",
      "B": "Has no effect on the solubility",
      "C": "Increases the pH of the solution",
      "D": "Increases the solubility of the ionic compound that shares the ion"
    },
    "answer": "A",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "Example of intermolecular forces include ______",
    "options": {
      "A": "Metallic bond",
      "B": "Hydrogen bonding",
      "C": "dative bond",
      "D": "Ionic bond"
    },
    "answer": "B",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "The mole ratio from a balanced chemical equation can be used to convert between ______",
    "options": {
      "A": "Masses of reactants and products",
      "B": "All of the above",
      "C": "Numbers of atoms or molecules",
      "D": "Volumes of gases"
    },
    "answer": "B",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "The mole is a unit used to represent a specific______",
    "options": {
      "A": "Mass",
      "B": "Volume",
      "C": "Number of atoms or molecules",
      "D": "Colour"
    },
    "answer": "C",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "A chemical reaction involves ___________",
    "options": {
      "A": "A physical change (like bending)",
      "B": "A change in state (like melting)",
      "C": "The rearrangement of atoms to form new substances",
      "D": "All of the above"
    },
    "answer": "C",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "A catalyst speeds up a chemical reaction by _______",
    "options": {
      "A": "Lowering the activation energy",
      "B": "Changing the products of the reaction",
      "C": "Being consumed in the reaction",
      "D": "All of the above"
    },
    "answer": "A",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "The substances undergoing a reaction are called ___________",
    "options": {
      "A": "Products",
      "B": "Reactants",
      "C": "Indicators",
      "D": "Catalysts"
    },
    "answer": "B",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "Electrolytes are substances that",
    "options": {
      "A": "Do not conduct electricity in solution",
      "B": "Are all acids",
      "C": "Conduct electricity in solution",
      "D": "Are all bases"
    },
    "answer": "C",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "In an ionic bond, one atom",
    "options": {
      "A": "donate and loses electron",
      "B": "Shares electrons equally",
      "C": "Loses electrons and becomes a cation",
      "D": "Doesn\\'t form ions"
    },
    "answer": "C",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "The law of conservation of mass states that in a chemical reaction ____",
    "options": {
      "A": "The number of protons is conserved",
      "B": "The number of neutrons is conserved",
      "C": "The total mass of reactants and products is conserved",
      "D": "The number of electrons is conserved"
    },
    "answer": "C",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following elements has the highest first ionization energy?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Be",
      "B": "Li",
      "C": "B",
      "D": "Na"
    },
    "answer": "A",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "Elements in group 1 (IA) are known as _______",
    "options": {
      "A": "Noble gases",
      "B": "Transition metals",
      "C": "Halogens",
      "D": "Alkali metals"
    },
    "answer": "D",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "Dmitri Mendeleev arranged elements on the periodic table in order of increasing atomic weight while Henry Moseley arranged the elements in order of increasing ____",
    "options": {
      "A": "boiling point",
      "B": "melting point",
      "C": "Isotopes",
      "D": "atomic number"
    },
    "answer": "D",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is NOT true about hydrogen?",
    "options": {
      "A": "It is the most abundant element in the universe",
      "B": "It is highly reactive with most elements",
      "C": "It forms compounds by losing or sharing electrons",
      "D": "It has a lower density than air"
    },
    "answer": "B",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "The maximum number of electrons allowed in a p orbital is _______",
    "options": {
      "A": 1,
      "B": 8,
      "C": 6,
      "D": 2
    },
    "answer": "D",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "The valence electrons of an element are the electrons in its ______",
    "options": {
      "A": "Outermost shell",
      "B": "Innermost shell",
      "C": "Nucleus",
      "D": "None of the above"
    },
    "answer": "A",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "The isotope of hydrogen with two neutrons is called ___________",
    "options": {
      "A": "Tritium",
      "B": "Hydrogen",
      "C": "Protium",
      "D": "Deuterium"
    },
    "answer": "A",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "Elements with a half-filled or completely filled subshell tend to have _______ ionization energy",
    "options": {
      "A": "higher",
      "B": "lower",
      "C": "no effect on",
      "D": "unpredictable"
    },
    "answer": "A",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following elements has the lowest first ionization energy?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Se",
      "B": "Carbon",
      "C": "K",
      "D": "Cu"
    },
    "answer": "C",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "The element formerly known as rutherfordium and Kurchotovium is now called ____",
    "options": {
      "A": "Nobelium",
      "B": "Unnilquadium",
      "C": "Lawrencium",
      "D": "Mendelevium"
    },
    "answer": "B",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "The process by which a heavy nucleus splits into smaller nuclei is called",
    "options": {
      "A": "Fusion",
      "B": "Fission",
      "C": "Radioactive decay",
      "D": "Electron capture"
    },
    "answer": "B",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following elements is a metalloid?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Sodium",
      "B": "Silicon",
      "C": "Gold",
      "D": "Hydrogen"
    },
    "answer": "B",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "The following is NOT true about complexation of alkali metals",
    "options": {
      "A": "Stability of alkali metal complexes decreases down the order Li > Na > K > Rb > Cs",
      "B": "Alkali metals form weak complexes due to their large size and low charge",
      "C": "Alkali metals form chelates with ligands like B-diketones",
      "D": "Lithium forms more complexes than other alkali metals due to its smaller size and higher polarizing power"
    },
    "answer": "A",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "Anomalous behavior of Lithium includes",
    "options": {
      "A": "All of the above",
      "B": "Higher melting and boiling point than other alkali metals",
      "C": "Reacting with water to form a nitride (Li3N)",
      "D": "Forming more soluble halides in organic solvents"
    },
    "answer": "A",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "When alkali metals react with atmospheric oxygen, they form:",
    "options": {
      "A": "Only superoxides",
      "B": "Only peroxides",
      "C": "Only normal oxides",
      "D": "Normal oxides, peroxides and superoxide"
    },
    "answer": "D",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "Metals are generally found on the ____",
    "options": {
      "A": "Right side of the periodic table",
      "B": "Left side of the periodic table",
      "C": "Top of the periodic table",
      "D": "Bottom of the periodic table"
    },
    "answer": "B",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "The process by which a heavy nucleus splits into smaller nuclei is called",
    "options": {
      "A": "Fission",
      "B": "Radioactive decay",
      "C": "Electron capture",
      "D": "Fusion"
    },
    "answer": "A",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "Alkali metals are strong reducing agents because ______",
    "options": {
      "A": "They have low electron affinity",
      "B": "They are highly electronegative",
      "C": "They form stable covalent bonds",
      "D": "They have high ionization energy"
    },
    "answer": "A",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "The following is NOT true about complexation of alkali metals",
    "options": {
      "A": "Alkali metals form chelates with ligands like B-diketones",
      "B": "Alkali metals form weak complexes due to their large size and low charge",
      "C": "Lithium forms more complexes than other alkali metals due to its smaller size and higher polarizing power",
      "D": "Stability of alkali metal complexes decreases down the order Li > Na > K > Rb > Cs"
    },
    "answer": "B",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following elements is a metalloid?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Sodium",
      "B": "Gold",
      "C": "Silicon",
      "D": "Hydrogen"
    },
    "answer": "C",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "Elements become more metallic as you move from",
    "options": {
      "A": "Top to bottom in a group",
      "B": "Left to right in a period",
      "C": "Top to bottom in a group",
      "D": "Left to right in a group"
    },
    "answer": "A",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is NOT true about isotopes?",
    "options": {
      "A": "They have different chemical properties",
      "B": "They have the same atomic number",
      "C": "They have the same mass number",
      "D": "They have different numbers of neutrons"
    },
    "answer": "A",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "An element is a substance which cannot be resolved into two or more simpler substances following any known _______ process.",
    "answer": "chemical",
    "type": "fill"
  },
  {
    "question": "Elements with atomic number greater than 100 follow IUPAC _______ rules.",
    "answer": "nomenclature",
    "type": "fill"
  },
  {
    "question": "Transition elements are characterized by the filling of _______ orbitals.",
    "answer": "d",
    "type": "fill"
  },
  {
    "question": "The general formula of hydrides of alkali metals is _______.",
    "answer": "MH",
    "type": "fill"
  },
  {
    "question": "When alkali metals react with water, they produce hydrogen gas and a _______.",
    "answer": "hydroxide",
    "type": "fill"
  },
  {
    "question": "The first period of the periodic table contains only _______ elements.",
    "answer": "two",
    "type": "fill"
  },
  {
    "question": "Atomic radius generally _______ down a group.",
    "answer": "increases",
    "type": "fill"
  },
  {
    "question": "John Newlands proposed the _______ of octaves.",
    "answer": "Law",
    "type": "fill"
  },
  {
    "question": "Tritium contains one proton and two _______.",
    "answer": "neutrons",
    "type": "fill"
  },
  {
    "question": "Mendeleev arranged elements in horizontal rows and vertical columns in order of increasing _______.",
    "answer": "atomic weight",
    "type": "fill"
  },
  {
    "question": "Lothar Meyer plotted atomic volume against _______.",
    "answer": "atomic weight",
    "type": "fill"
  },
  {
    "question": "The first scientist to point out a systematic relationship among the elements was _______.",
    "answer": "J.W. Dobereiner",
    "type": "fill"
  },
  {
    "question": "Hydrogen bonding affects the _______ and melting points of compounds.",
    "answer": "boiling",
    "type": "fill"
  },
  {
    "question": "Hydrogen forms compounds with most elements except _______.",
    "answer": "noble gases",
    "type": "fill"
  },
  {
    "question": "Ionization energy generally _______ across a period.",
    "answer": "increases",
    "type": "fill"
  },
  {
    "question": "Combination of two or more elements chemically form a new substance called _______.",
    "answer": "compounds",
    "type": "fill"
  },
  {
    "question": "Hydrogen can act as both a _______ and a non-metal.",
    "answer": "metal",
    "type": "fill"
  },
  {
    "question": "The maximum number of electrons that can occupy a d subshell is _______.",
    "answer": "10",
    "type": "fill"
  },
  {
    "question": "The periodic law states that the properties of elements are periodic functions of their _______.",
    "answer": "atomic numbers",
    "type": "fill"
  },
  {
    "question": "The anomalous behavior of beryllium is due to its small atomic size and high _______.",
    "answer": "polarizing power",
    "type": "fill"
  },
  {
    "question": "Lanthanides involve the filling of _______ orbitals.",
    "answer": "4f",
    "type": "fill"
  },
  {
    "question": "Hund\u2019s rule states that electrons occupy each orbital singly before _______ occurs.",
    "answer": "pairing",
    "type": "fill"
  },
  {
    "question": "The modern periodic law states that the properties of elements are periodic functions of their _______.",
    "answer": "atomic numbers",
    "type": "fill"
  },
  {
    "question": "The stability of alkali metal carbonates _______ down the group.",
    "answer": "increases",
    "type": "fill"
  },
  {
    "question": "Actinides involve the filling of _______ orbitals.",
    "answer": "5f",
    "type": "fill"
  },
  {
    "question": "The IUPAC recommended Arabic numerals from 1 to _______ for group numbering.",
    "answer": "18",
    "type": "fill"
  },
  {
    "question": "Electron affinity generally _______ across a period.",
    "answer": "increases",
    "type": "fill"
  },
  {
    "question": "Electronegativity is the tendency of an atom to attract _______ towards itself.",
    "answer": "electrons",
    "type": "fill"
  },
  {
    "question": "Lithium forms stronger complexes than other alkali metals because of its high _______.",
    "answer": "polarizing power",
    "type": "fill"
  },
  {
    "question": "The solubility of alkaline earth metal hydroxides _______ down the group.",
    "answer": "increases",
    "type": "fill"
  },
  {
    "question": "Inorganic Chemistry is the study of chemical elements and their compounds excluding compounds of _______.",
    "answer": "carbon",
    "type": "fill"
  },
  {
    "question": "The most common isotope of hydrogen is called _______.",
    "answer": "Protium",
    "type": "fill"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Aufbau principle describes the sequence in which electrons fill _______.",
    "answer": "atomic orbitals",
    "type": "fill"
  },
  {
    "question": "Alkali metals are found in group _______ of the periodic table.",
    "answer": "1",
    "type": "fill"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to Mendeleev, the properties of any element are an average of the properties of its _______.",
    "answer": "neighbours",
    "type": "fill"
  },
  {
    "question": "The anomalous behavior of lithium is due to its small _______ and high charge density.",
    "answer": "size",
    "type": "fill"
  },
  {
    "question": "When alkali metals dissolve in liquid ammonia, the solution appears _______ in color.",
    "answer": "blue",
    "type": "fill"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Pauli Exclusion Principle states that no two electrons can have the same set of four _______.",
    "answer": "quantum numbers",
    "type": "fill"
  },
  {
    "question": "Deuterium contains one proton and one _______.",
    "answer": "neutron",
    "type": "fill"
  },
  {
    "question": "Alkaline earth metals are found in group _______ of the periodic table.",
    "answer": "2",
    "type": "fill"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the modern periodic table, elements are arranged in seven horizontal rows called _______.",
    "answer": "periods",
    "type": "fill"
  },
  {
    "question": "The reactivity of alkali metals _______ down the group.",
    "answer": "increases",
    "type": "fill"
  },
  {
    "question": "Henry Moseley discovered that atomic number is a more fundamental property than _______.",
    "answer": "atomic weight",
    "type": "fill"
  },
  {
    "question": "A balanced chemical equation shows _______",
    "options": {
      "A": "The reactants and products, with their coefficients indicating quantities",
      "B": "The reactants and products, but not the quantities",
      "C": "The rate of the reaction",
      "D": "The energy change during the reaction"
    },
    "answer": "A",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "Lewis structures use symbols to represent ________",
    "options": {
      "A": "Isotopes",
      "B": "Protons",
      "C": "Electrons",
      "D": "Neutrons"
    },
    "answer": "C",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "In an ionic bond, one atom",
    "options": {
      "A": "Shares electrons equally",
      "B": "donate and loses electron",
      "C": "Doesn't form ions",
      "D": "Loses electrons and becomes a cation"
    },
    "answer": "D",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "A chemical reaction involves ___________",
    "options": {
      "A": "A change in state (like melting)",
      "B": "All of the above",
      "C": "The rearrangement of atoms to form new substances",
      "D": "A physical change (like bending)"
    },
    "answer": "C",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "The law of conservation of mass states that in a chemical reaction _________-",
    "options": {
      "A": "The number of electrons is conserved",
      "B": "The total mass of reactants and products is conserved",
      "C": "The number of neutrons is conserved",
      "D": "The number of protons is conserved"
    },
    "answer": "B",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "The attraction between a partially positive hydrogen atom and a partially negative atom in another molecule is called a _________",
    "options": {
      "A": "Metallic bond",
      "B": "Hydrogen bond",
      "C": "Covalent bond",
      "D": "Dipole-dipole interaction"
    },
    "answer": "B",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "The substances undergoing a reaction are called ___________",
    "options": {
      "A": "Indicators",
      "B": "Reactants",
      "C": "Products",
      "D": "Catalysts"
    },
    "answer": "B",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "The mole ratio from a balanced chemical equation can be used to convert between ______",
    "options": {
      "A": "All of the above",
      "B": "Volumes of gases",
      "C": "Masses of reactants and products",
      "D": "Numbers of atoms or molecules"
    },
    "answer": "A",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "The common ion effect describes how the presence of a common ion in a solution",
    "options": {
      "A": "Has no effect on the solubility",
      "B": "Increases the pH of the solution",
      "C": "Increases the solubility of the ionic compound that shares the ion",
      "D": "Reduces the solubility of the ionic compound that shares the ion"
    },
    "answer": "D",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a metallic bond, electrons are __________",
    "options": {
      "A": "Delocalized in a 'sea' throughout the metal",
      "B": "Localized around individual atoms",
      "C": "Shared between two atoms",
      "D": "Not involved in bonding"
    },
    "answer": "A",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is NOT true about hydrogen?",
    "options": {
      "A": "It is the most abundant element in the universe",
      "B": "It forms compounds by losing or sharing electrons",
      "C": "It has a lower density than air",
      "D": "It is highly reactive with most elements"
    },
    "answer": "B",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "Elements in the same period (row) have the same:",
    "options": {
      "A": "Number of electron shells",
      "B": "Number of neutrons",
      "C": "Number of protons",
      "D": "Number of valence electrons"
    },
    "answer": "A",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "Dmitri Mendeleev arranged elements on the periodic table in order of increasing atomic weight while Henry Moseley arranged the elements in order of increasing _________",
    "options": {
      "A": "boiling point",
      "B": "Isotopes",
      "C": "atomic number",
      "D": "melting point"
    },
    "answer": "C",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "The lightest and most abundant element in the universe is ________",
    "options": {
      "A": "Carbon",
      "B": "Hydrogen",
      "C": "Oxygen",
      "D": "Helium"
    },
    "answer": "B",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "Elements with a half-filled or completely filled subshell tend to have _______ ionization energy",
    "options": {
      "A": "no effect on",
      "B": "unpredictable",
      "C": "lower",
      "D": "higher"
    },
    "answer": "D",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "The separation of hydrogen isotopes can be achieved through ________",
    "options": {
      "A": "Fractional distillation",
      "B": "Physical methods",
      "C": "Chemical reactions",
      "D": "Centrifugation"
    },
    "answer": "A",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following elements has the highest first ionization energy?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Na",
      "B": "B",
      "C": "Be",
      "D": "Li"
    },
    "answer": "B",
    "type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "question": "The maximum number of electrons allowed in a p orbital is _______",
    "options": {
      "A": "2",
      "B": "1",
      "C": "8",
      "D": "6"
    },
    "answer": "A",
    "type": "mcq"
  }
]